University Railroad Collection 1997.0041
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
University Railroad Collection
undated, 1841-1993.
1997.0041
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Libraries
65.0 Linear feet
This is an artificial collection of publications, timetables, forms, reports, track diagrams and charts, equipment blueprints, maps, drawings and artwork, and photographs almost exclusively associated with the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and its predecessor railroad lines, gathered from many donors and purchases.
65 linear feet.
University of Connecticut (Collector).
History
For almost one hundred years the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, better known as the New Haven Railroad, was the primary means of passenger and freight transportation in southern New England. Chartered in 1872, this merger between the New York & New Haven and Hartford & New Haven railroads later included the long desired rail link between Boston and New York. Approximately one hundred small independent railroads were built in southern New England between 1826 and the 1880s. By 1904, the majority were absorbed into the vast New Haven system. At its peak in 1929, the New Haven Railroad owned and operated 2,131 miles of track throughout eastern New York, Connecticut, Massachusetts, and Rhode Island.
The local railroad lines that eventually became part of the New Haven system developed in response to local business and transportation needs. Unlike the Western states, where railroads preceded and shaped settlement, in the Northeast they served primarily to link existing towns, businesses, and markets. The New Haven system thus developed as a result of numerous consolidations and mergers. The New Haven traced its founding to 1826, when one of its predecessor companies originated, but the New York, New Haven and Hartford Railroad was not chartered until 1872. The company followed the pattern of consolidation established by the Pennsylvania Railroad and other companies, particularly after 1889, when major lines in Connecticut, Rhode Island, and southern Massachusetts provided a strong network linking New York and Boston. By 1890, company revenue exceeded $100,000,000 per year, and the New Haven employed 4,000 people to serve twelve million passengers annually.
This success led a wealthy group of New York investors, headed by J. Pierpont Morgan, to seek and gain control of the New Haven's board. In 1903, Morgan installed Charles Mellen as president of the railroad. Together Morgan and Mellen set out to achieve a complete monopoly of transportation in New England. Substantial improvements to the system were made during the Mellen years, including electrification of rail lines between Woodlawn, New York, and New Haven, Connecticut, and construction of a power generating plant in Cos Cob, Connecticut. These accomplishments, however, were overshadowed by Morgan's ambitious schemes to dominate all modes of transportation in New England. Steamboat lines, trolley companies, and other railroad lines were purchased regardless of price and incorporated into the New Haven system.
An investigation of the New Haven's activities by Louis Brandeis in 1907 revealed the overextended railroad was on the verge of financial collapse. Morgan's death in 1913 and Mellen's subsequent resignation brought to a close a stormy period in the New Haven's history.
During the First World War, all of the railroads in the United States, including the New Haven Railroad, were operated by the federal government. After the war, under Edward Pearson, President through 1928, the railroad was able to recover partially, despite increasing competition from automobiles, by sharing in the national economic growth of the 1920s. The company tried to meet this transportation competition by forming the New England Transportation Company, which operated a fleet of trucks and buses. Recovery of the New Haven, however, was cut short by the Depression of the 1930s, and in 1935 the New Haven plunged into bankruptcy. The company remained in trusteeship until 1947, when it returned to private ownership.
A series of struggles for control of the company in the post World War II period severely weakened the management of the company and its ability to adapt to changes in the transportation industry. The completion of the Connecticut Turnpike and other superhighways and the start of air shuttle service between Boston and New York intensified competition. The company's historic liability as a railroad overburdened with many short, costly branch lines further accelerated its decline.
On 7 July 1961, the New Haven Railroad once again went into receivership. A seven year trusteeship period followed, culminating in the absorption of the New Haven in the Penn Central system on 1 January 1969. Three years later the Penn Central itself collapsed into bankruptcy. The former components of the New Haven Railroad were divided among several entities. Freight service was assumed by Conrail when it was formed in 1976, although the Providence & Worcester also provided freight service on portions of the former New Haven, as did a few other operators. Passenger commuter service was funded by the New York Metropolitan Transit Authority and the Connecticut Department of Transportation. Long-haul passenger service was provided by Amtrak beginning in 1971. After 1976 passenger commuter service was operated by Conrail. In 1982, the United States Congress passed legislation that forced Conrail to divest itself of its commuter rail lines. On 1 January 1983, Metro-North Commuter Railroad, under joint ownership of the states of New York and Connecticut, took over all commuter passenger service. Amtrak continued to handle all long-haul passenger service.
The history of the New Haven Railroad reveals a company formed by one of the classic merger and consolidation patterns of the late 19th century, which was later unable to respond effectively to major changes in the transportation industry. The company's rapid growth, collapse, temporary recovery, and final dissolution offer a dramatic story, with government regulation, internal management decisions, and market competition playing important roles in the company's history.
Scope and Content
This is an artificial collection of publications, timetables, forms, reports, track diagrams and charts, equipment blueprints, maps, drawings and artwork, and photographs almost exclusively associated with the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and its predecessor railroad lines, gathered from many donors and purchases.
Arrangement
Series I: Papers, undated, 1841-1993, consists of writings, instructions, timetables and memoranda involving the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad's various operations, predecessors, stations and work processes. The later material, including employee timetables and rosters, is from Penn Central, Amtrak and Conrail, particularly their Northeast region operations, and Metro-North Commuter Railroad. The materials are organized chronologically.
Series II: Track Diagrams and Charts, Maps, Equipment Blueprints, Surveyor's Field Books, Drawings, and Artwork, undated, 1841-1984, are arranged as separate subseries.
Subseries A, Track Diagrams, shows property of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and many predecessors lines including as the Berkshire Railroad and the Holyoke & Westfield Railroad.
Subseries B, Maps, is arranged by item and thereunder chronologically of maps of properties of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and several of its predecessors. Of particular interest are maps of the Belle Dock railroad terminal in New Haven, Connecticut.
Subseries C, Equipment Blueprints, are of equipment designed and used by the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad. They are arranged by an item number represented on each drawing.
Subseries D consists of 32 surveyor's field books, circa 1919-1927, consisting of surveys of property owned by the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, done by the Real Estate and Right of Way Department from the general offices in New Haven, Connecticut. The field books show drawings of property in Connecticut, showing meticulous drawings of property owned by the railroad.
Subseries E, Drawings and Artwork, includes drawings of New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad locomotives by William Dulmaine, Jr., and " Heidorn."
Series III: Photographs, 1930s-1995, includes images of locomotives and cars of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, the New Haven, Connecticut, railroad station, and of policemen employed by the railroad. Also of special interest are station surveys, done in 1954-1955, of stations along the New Haven District and the New York District, with photographs taken by Charles B. Gunn, who served as company photographer at that time.
Series IV: Gift of Gary Carlquist, undated, 1897-1984, consists of forms, letters, photographs, rule books, anual reports, track plans, keys, ticket punchers, and drawings associated with the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and its predecessors. The materials are listed in no particular order.
Series V: Gift of Carl Leaman, ( 1858-1944 ) is composed almost exclusively of timetables for the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and its predecessor railroad lines of the Hartford, Providence & Fishkill Railroad, the New York, Providence & Boston Railroad, the Connecticut Valley Railroad, the Old Colony Railroad, and the Lowell and Lawrence Railroad. They are organized by railroad. It also includes a writing about the electrification of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and a listing of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad station numbers.
Related Material
Archives & Special Collections has a substantial collection of materials pertaining to New England railroads. For detailed information on these collections please contact the curator or ask at the reference desk.
Provenance and Acquisition
This is an artificial collection of papers, timetables, blueprints, maps, publications and photographs gathered from many different donors or, for a very few items, of purchases from dealers. Materials of note were graciously donated by the following persons:
The maps of the Connecticut Railroad Commissioners were donated by Max Miller of Higganum, Connecticut.
The child's coloring book was donated by Norman Stevens of Storrs, Connecticut.
Many of the materials in Series I and the track diagrams of Series II were donated in October 2006 by Sandy Abbati in loving memory of her relatives Paul LaBerge, Joseph LaBerge and Artie Lynch, who were employed by the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and its successors.
The 1969 photograph of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Police Department was donated in May 2007 by Frederick Chidester Sr. of Milford, Connecticut.
The Hartford, Connecticut, Windsor Street Yard track map, the 1946 New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Boston office telephone directory, and the 1928 smallpox file were donated in July 2007 and May 2008 by Stanislaus Whittlesey of Little Rock, Arkansas. All of the items in Box 52 were donated by Mr. Whittlesey in June 2011 and November 2012.
The materials in 28:114 were collected from the South Norwalk, Connecticut, freight depot, and were donated by Mr. John R. Iacovino of Wallace, North Carolina. Mr. Iacovino also donated all materials in 59:133 in October 2012.
The timetables in 28:112 were donated in May 2009 by Beth Magura of Stafford Springs, Connecticut.
The Surveyor's Field Books in Box 29 were donated in 2003 by the Connecticut Department of Transportation.
The materials in Box 27 and the photographs of the New Haven, Connecticut, railroad station were donated in July 2009 by Gary Carlquist, formerly of Branford, Connecticut.
The photographs taken by Joseph P. Boreskie of Gretna, Manitoba, Canada, were donated in September 2009 by his son Tom Boreskie of Toronto, Ontario, Canada.
The photographs of railroad cars of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, taken outside of their usual territory and the 1944 article from Enginemen's Magazine were donated in October 2009 by Gary Stengle of North Platte, Nebraska.
The timetables in 28:107 were donated in October 2008, November 2009, and December 2010 by Carl Leaman of Westport, Connecticut.
The glass negative of a railroad bridge in Naugatuck, Connecticut, was donated by Charles Dunn of Naugatuck in 2002.
The station surveys in Boxes 54-57 were donated by Frank N. Morrissey of Braintree, Massachusetts, in September 2011. The materials in 60:136 and all of the contents of Box 61 were donated by Mr. Morrissey in March 2012.
The August 1955 Menu & Travel Guide was donated in 2000 by Cristiana Graham.
The track diagrams and Ridgefield & New York Railroad items in 52:129 were donated in August 2012 by John R. Iacovino of Wallace, North Carolina.
The Connecticut Valley Railroad timetable at 59:132 was donated in November 2012 by Kim Sheridan of Essex, Connecticut.
The timetables in 59:134 were donated in March 2012 by Carol Stoller of Newton, Massachusetts.
The blueprints and diagrams in 60:135 were donated by the Baltimore & Ohio Historical Society of Baltimore, Maryland, in December 2011.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Amtrak.; Berkshire Railroad.; Bonjiorno, Joseph A.; Boston and Maine Railroad.; Cambridge Electric Light Company.; Central Vermont Railway Co.; ConRail.; Consolidated Railway Company.; Corrigan, Matthew; Danbury & Norwalk Railroad.; Dulmaine, William Jr.; Fales & Jenks Machine Company.; Hartford & New Haven Railroad.; Hartford, Providence & Fishkill Railroad Company.; Holyoke & Westfield Railroad.; Housatonic Railroad.; Hudson River & Portchester Railroad.; LaBerge, Paul; Lowell and Lawrence Railroad.; Meriden, Southington and Compounce Tramway.; Metro-North Commuter Railroad.; New Haven & Northampton Railroad.; New York & New England Railroad.; New York, New London & Stonington Railroad.; New York, Providence & Boston Railroad.; Old Colony Railroad.; Pearson, Edward J.; Penn Central Transportation Company.; Providence and Worcestor Railroad Company.; Railroad yards.; Salem & Lowell Railroad.; Shore Line Electric Railway.; Stockbridge & Pittsfield Railroad.; Torrington & Winchester Street Railway Company.; West Stockbridge Railroad.; Windsor Locks & Suffield Railroad.; Administrative Records.; Blueprints.; Books.; Boston (Mass.); Bylaws.; Cedar Hill (Conn.); Correspondence.; Financial Records.; Grand Central Terminal (New York, N.Y.); Groton (Conn.); Hamden (Mass.); Harrison (N.Y.); Hartford (Conn.); Manchester (Conn.); Maps.; Maybrook (N.Y.); Middletown (Conn.); Minutes.; Mount Vernon (N.Y.); New Haven (Conn.); Notebooks.; Old Saybrook (Conn.); Photocopies.; Photographs.; Publications.; Railroads -- Connecticut.; Railroads -- Massachusetts.; Railroads -- New York (State).; Railroads -- Rhode Island.; Rye (N.Y.); South Lyme (Conn.); Springfield (Mass.); Stonington (Conn.); Timetables.; Westchester (N.Y.); Willimantic (Conn.); Woonsocket (R.I.)
- Series I: Papers, undated, 1841-1993
  - Information about the Flowers Sleeping Car Company, with an article, "A Real Sleeper," written by Michael J. Sullivan, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - An All-Time Listing of the Stations of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad and of its Predecessors and Successors, compiled by John F. Dias, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Certificate for stock in the Hartford & New Haven Railroad Company, 1841 (Box 15, Folder 100)
  - Receipt for transportation of merchandise of the Housatonic Railroad Company, 1869 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Timetable, Connecticut Valley Railroad, [1870s] (Box 59, Folder 132)
  - Timetables (on film), 1890-1941 (Box 58)
  - Timetables, 1893-1907 (Box 60, Folder 136)
    Scope and Content Note
    [Materials include: Two employees timetables for New York and New England Railroad (western division), January 15, 1893 and May 7, 1893 (large format); Seven large format employee timetables of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, 1895-1907]
  - Documents about land in Orange, Connecticut, owned by John R. Hamilton, purchased by the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, 1894 (Box 12, Folder 113)
  - Three receipts from the Cambridge Electric Light Company in Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1895-1896, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Torrington & Winchester Street Railway Company cash book, 1900-1907 (Box 19)
  - Brochures of the Railway Safety Gate manufactured by the Fales & Jenks Machine Company of Pawtucket, Rhode Island, 1903, 1918 (Box 28, Folder 115)
  - Letter concerning a freight bill to the auditor of the Consolidated Railway Company, 1905 (Box 15, Folder 101)
  - Waybills for Central New England Railway freight, 1905 (Box 52, Folder 119)
  - Correspondence between engineers and contractors concerning the construction or improvement of a bridge in Woonsocket, Rhode Island, and other infrastructure in the urban Rhode Island corridor, 1906-1907 (Box 15, Folder 102)
  - Torrington & Winchester Street Railway Company register of vouchers, 1907 (Box 18)
  - Writings about railroad wrecks on the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, in 1911 and 1913, 1911, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence about a bridge in South Walpole, Massachusetts, 1918-1929 (Box 52, Folder 123)
  - Excerpt from "Operating Requirements of the New Haven System" by E. J. Pearson (typescript copies of memo), 1920, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Typescript correspondence from E. J. Pearson about train rating schedules, 1924, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Typescript correspondence from E. J. Pearson to New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad employees about the general organization of the company, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Estimate for girder bridge at Toelles Crossing in Wallingford, Connecticut, 1927 (Box 52, Folder 125)
  - Correspondence about bridge no. 0.49 in North Attleboro, Massachusetts, 1927-1930 (Box 52, Folder 126)
  - Correspondence to New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad administrators to encourage employees to get vaccinated against smallpox, 1928 (Box 15, Folder 103)
  - Monthly commutation ticket between New York and Pelham, New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Timetables, New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, 1940, 1955 (Box 59, Folder 134)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, Rules for the Government of the Operating Department, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hatch, P.H. "Diesel-electric Locomotives in Road Service," Enginemen's Magazine, 1944 June (Box 28, Folder 109)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad telephone directory, Boston office, 1946 July 29 (Box 28, Folder 110)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad memorandum of general instructions for the detouring of trains, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Excerpts from an address by S. F. Mackay at the New England Railroad Club about the responsibilities of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Transportation Department, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Memorandum to the secretaries and stenographers of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad with instructions on writing letters for the signature of heads of other departments, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Memorandum about the office practice covering the method of handling over dimension shipments, New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Maybrook, New York, Classification Yard description, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Description of the Cedar Hill, Connecticut, railroad yard, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Miniature Bridge List, New Haven Division, New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, 1948 January 2 (Box 28, Folder 117)
  - Providence & Worcester Railroad Company stockholders ledger, 1950 September 18 (Box 17)
  - Quiz on Railroads and Railroading, published by the Association of American Railroads, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Memorandum from the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Transporation Department about the effects on the railroad of a switchmen work stoppage from 1951 January 30 - February 6, in Chicago (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Menu & Travel Guide [of the] New Haven Railroad, 1955 August (Box 52, Folder 128)
  - Memorandum from the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Transportation Department about freight schedules, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Memorandum from the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Transporation Department about per diem statistics, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, Rules for the Government of the Operating Department, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Financial and Statistical Supplement to Stockholders Report of the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Year 1955, 1956 March 28 (Box 28, Folder 116)
  - Memorandum from the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Transportation Department about the estimated annual reduction in passenger train miles, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, Timetable no. 10, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, Timetable no. 14, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Forms and freight reports gathered from the South Norwalk, Connecticut, freight depot, 1964-1970 (Box 28, Folder 114)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, Telephone Directory, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, Description of Passenger Equipment, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Pennsylvania Railroad Electrical Operating Instructions, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Summary of Equipment, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Public Grade Crossings in Massachusetts and Rhode Island, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Timetables for the Boston & Maine Railroad and the New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, 1967-1970 (Box 28, Folder 112)
  - Penn Central Special Instructions Governing Operation of Signals and Interlockings for Train Dispatchers, Train Directors, Operators and Levermen, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Penn Central Safety Rules, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Penn Central Rules of Conducting Transportation, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Arranged Freight Service Symbol Book, no. 23, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad Time Table no. 25, for Employes Only, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Penn Central, New Haven Region, Passenger Train Miles, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Penn Central, Brake and Train Air Signal Instructions,Penn Central, Brake and Train Air Signal Instructions, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Freight shippers on New Haven region of Penn Central, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Penn Central, New Haven Region, TimeTable no. 26, for Employes Only, 1969 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Penn Central, New Haven Region, TimeTable no. 1, for Employes Only, 1969 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Penn Central, New Haven Region, List of Station Numbers and Junction Points, 1969 August 1 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Penn Central, Hazardous Materials Regulations, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Penn Central, General Notice no. 207 (the clearance authority for the movement of all equipment and all lading on open top cars), 1969 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Form for the agreement between Penn Central and its employes of the former New York, New Haven & Hartford Railroad, represented by the American Train Dispatchers Association, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Penn Central Train dispatcher seniority rosters, 1970, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Penn Central Metropolitan Region Timetable no. 1, for employes only, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Penn Central, New Haven Region, TimeTable no. 2, for Employes Only, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Penn Central, New Haven Region, TimeTable no. 3, for Employes Only, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 47)